Beth: All individuals with autism have a
unique set of strengths and abilities and
to help them reach their full potential
it is important to identify them.
Once identified working with these
strengths can be a way of helping improve
their general motivation and development.
Some individuals with autism will
be very driven by their particular
skills and interests and if
these are utilised appropriately,
they can increase motivation.
let’s look at some examples of
strengths commonly associated with
autism and especially individuals
that are high functioning.
- Joe: Specialist knowledge and
a high motivation in topics and
activities that are of interest.
- Exceptional memory for facts and
figures and the ability to carry
out mathematical tasks mentally
with a high degree of accuracy.
- An innovative approach to problem solving.
- Innate skills in creative arts,
such as Art and Music and use
of memory to enhance this.
- Enthusiasm for favourite interests with a
drive to share this enjoyment with others.
- Good almost obsessive attention to
detail and ability to follow instructions
especially when taught correctly.
- A tendency to be honest and plain talking
- Ability to see the world from
a different perspective and can
bring a different insight to things
Beth: By working with and supporting the
individual to bolster their strengths and
abilities, a person with Autism should
be enabled to reach their potential and
focus on what motivates them, and in turn
this should improve their confidence and
self-worth in all aspects of their life.